<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.21.2 -->
<document source="/home/runner/work/embc23/embc23/source/publishing/index.rst" translation_progress="{'total': 0, 'translated': 0}" xmlns:c="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:changeset="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:citation="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:cite="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:cpp="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:footcite="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:index="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:js="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:math="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:py="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:rst="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/" xmlns:std="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/">
    <section ids="publishing" names="publishing">
        <title>Publishing</title>
        <paragraph>The <reference name="Physiome journal" refuri="https://journal.physiomeproject.org">Physiome journal</reference> is a place where scientists can submit the implementation of their model in a reproducible format. <emphasis>Physiome</emphasis> articles must be associated with a primary publication in a traditional peer-reviewed journal - the <emphasis>Physiome</emphasis> review process only reviews the reproducibility of the implementation, not the quality of the science.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>A <emphasis>Physiome</emphasis> article provides a forum for more in-depth discussion and presentation of the model implementation than what is traditionally seen in journal articles. Enabling authors to present much of the detailed knowledge that goes into the model and which is needed for others to better evaluate the model for suitability for a given future task.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>Currently, <emphasis>Physiome</emphasis> articles are a static presentation of the model implementation, with readers able to download the COMBINE Archive associated with the article to obtain the complete implementation needed to reuse the model. Going forward, we are looking at how to take advantage of the rapidly evolving web-based technologies that will enable more dynamic, interactive presentation and exploration of published articles.</paragraph>
        <target ids="physiome-journal" names="physiome\ journal" refuri="https://journal.physiomeproject.org"></target>
    </section>
</document>
